Smith, Edwin S. Papers 5549
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Edwin S. Smith Papers
1903-1978
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Smith, Edwin S.
5549
11 cubic feet
11 linear ft.
Papers (documents).
Correspondence, poetry, manuscripts, transcripts and papers collected and written by Edwin S. Smith.
5661773
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, June 01, 2012
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, June 05, 2019
Biographical / Historical
1891 Born November 12th, Brookline, Massachusetts
1915 Harvard University, A.B. Degree
1915-17 Newspaper reporter in Hartford and Springfield
Married Marion Long (October 20,1917), Framingham, Massachusetts
Conducted research on industrial relations at Dennison Manufacturing Company and for the Russell Sage Foundation
1924-30 Personnel Manager, Filene's Department Store
Personal Assistant to A. Lincoln Filene
1930-33 Commissioner, Massachusetts Department of Labor and Industries
1933 Official Observer to the International Labor Conference in Geneva
1933-34 Member, National Labor Board under the National Recovery Act
1934-41 Member, National Labor Relations Board under the National Labor Relations Act
1941-42 National Director, Oil Workers Organizing Campaign, CIO
1942-45 Executive Director, National Council of American-Soviet Friendship
1947-49 Teacher of History, Putney School, Vermont
1949-52 Director, National Teachers Division, United Public Workers of America
1952-64 Owner and Manager, Am-Rus Literary and Music Agency, also Sovfoto and Eastfoto Agency
1964 Retired to Sag Harbor, New York
1976 November 27th, died at age 85
Scope and Contents
This is a collection of correspondence, poetry, manuscripts, transcripts and papers collected and written by Edwin S. Smith.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Arrangement
Series I. Personal Papers
Sub-Series A. Correspondence 1925-1974 Sub-Series B. Speeches, 1905-1950 Sub-Series C. Writings Sub-Series D. Miscellaneous
Series II. Research Files
Series III. History of the National Labor Relations Board
Series IV. Additional Papers 1932-1971
Sub-Series A. Correspondence Sub-Series B. Subject Files Sub-Series C. Miscellaneous
Smith, Edwin S.
5661773
- Series I. Personal Papers
  - Sub-Series A. Correspondence 1925-1974
    - Correspondence, 1925-1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Includes personal letter to "Dunny ..." discussing Freud's "Beyond the Pleasure Principle" and "Group Psychology and the Analysis of the Ego"; poetry from Henry S. Dennison; Correspondence with Franklin Delano Roosevelt (Governor of the State of New York, and as President of the United States) regarding Smith's appointments to the positions of Massachusetts Commissioner of Labor and Industries (1931) and Executive Member of the National Labor Relations Board (NLRB) (1934); Smith's letter of resignation from the NLRB to President Roosevelt and abbreviated version to Frances Perkins (Secretary of Labor).
    - Correspondence, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Substantial correspondence from officials of the American Federation of Hosiery Workers concerning the Berkshire Knitting Mills strike. Includes 13pp brief discussing wages, sex discrimination, and breakdown of collective bargaining. Also of interest are news releases describing Reading, Pennsylvania manufacturers' admiration for Hitler and fascist Germany's labor policies.
    - Correspondence, 1938-1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      To Winston Churchill, Esq., M.P. regarding economic boycotts against fascist nations; Text of speech "The Basis of a Good Neighbor Policy" and related correspondence to Hon. Sumner Welles (Acting Secretary of State) and Ellis O. Briggs (Acting Chief, Division of the American Republics).
    - Correspondence, 1940-1948 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Lengthy (20pp+) correspondence documenting Edwin S. Smith's (Director, National Council of American-Soviet Friendship, Inc.) trip to the Soviet Union (6/45-7/45). Includes detailed account of early passenger aviation; descriptions of Tripoli, Cairo, Moscow and Kiev, as well as meetings with cultural heroes such as Prokoviev, Shostakovich, Kabalevsky and Eisenstein.
    - Correspondence, 1956-1959 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Subpoena to appear before Committee on Un-American Activities of the House of Representatives; Discussion of Edwin Smith's (Am-Rus Literary and Music Agency) review of books on Henry David Thoreau, from Walter Harding (Professor, Teachers College, Geneseo, N.Y.), Leo Stoller (Professor, Dept. of English, Wayne State University and author of After Walden) and Truman Nelson; from Edwin Smith to Dr. Annette Rubinstein regarding Jacksonian democracy and Thoreau.
    - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Copy of Edwin Smith's "A Thoreau for Today" (Mainstream, April 1960) and related correspondence from: Paul Sherman (author of The Shores of America, Thoreau's Exploration), Leslie C. Dunn (Professor, Dept. of Zoology, Columbia University), Dirk Struck, Leo Stoller and Lola S. Haverstick.
    - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Personal correspondence from Mary Van Kleeck; Copy of editorial entitled "Comment on Harvey Swados' `The West Coast Waterfront' Dissent, Autumn 1961" (10pp), sent to Smith by Lincoln Fairley (Research Director, International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union.)
    - Correspondence, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Correspondence with Lincoln Fairley regarding Mechanization and Modernization Agreement funds; Copy to Edwin Smith of Ernest DeMaio's (President, United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America) letter to Raymond Dennis (International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers Toronto, Canada) concerning the Common Market's impact on the U.S. economy; table of Man-Days Lost Through Industrial Disputes in Selected Industries in France and Germany.
    - Correspondence, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      George Meany's opening remarks before the International Confederation of Free Trade Unions; Excerpt of M. J. Furay's manuscript The Forces And Events Which Led To The Institutionalization Of Unions In The American Way Of Life And The Impact Of That Process Upon Our Society And Culture (8pp); correspondence from Dr. Charles P. Larrowe and Lincoln Fairley regarding Smith's prospectus for his manuscript History of Labor.
    - Correspondence, 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Lengthy criticism of Michael Eisner's (possibly a graduate student at the University of Wisconsin) manuscript discussing the role William Leiserson played on the NLRB (12pp); personal letter from Harvard classmate Carlyle Morris; hate mail from reactionaries.
    - Correspondence, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Report entitled Deregistration of "D" Men, San Francisco, 1963-1964 (15pp); to Lincoln Fairley summarizing "leading ideas" discussed in Smith's manuscript History of Labor (4pp).
    - Correspondence, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      To Hon. J. William Fulbright (Senator, Foreign Relations Committee) commending the committee on hearings it conducted regarding American military operations in Vietnam; Joseph Polowsky's (member, 1st American army patrol to meet the Soviet army at the Elbe River in Germany on 3/25/45) proposed resolution recommending the five permanent members of the United Nations Security Council celebrate April 25 as a holiday of reconciliation, cooperation and rededication; letter of support to Senator Eugene McCarthy in his campaign for the Presidency; copy of letter to Coretta Scott King (Mrs. Martin Luther King, Jr.) from John W. Willoughby (Friends of the Library of Southampton College) requesting permission to name a collection on Black history and culture "The Martin Luther King, Jr. Collection".
    - Correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Personal correspondence between Edwin Smith and Mark Heming (friend from Sag Harbor). Includes Heming's accounts of his experiences in London.
    - Correspondence, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Personal correspondence between Edwin Smith and Mark Heming. Includes a discussion of Nixon and Watergate, as well as Smith's review of a film on the Chinese Communist Revolution. Personal letter from Thomas I. Emerson (Yale University Law School, formerly of the NLRB); poetry exchange with Marian Curtiss; personal letter from Moses Soyer (friend and member of the Artists Committee of the National Council of American Soviet Friendship) regarding "Ida".
  - Sub-Series B. Speeches, 1905-1950
    - Speeches, 1905-1932 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Item 1: The Lumber Dealer Needs Cooperative Research, 1928; Speech (Box 1, Folder 15)
        1/26/28.
      - Item 2: Will Ethical Practices Help Solve Merchandising Problems, 1928; Speech (Box 1, Folder 15)
        Before the New England Section of National Association of Stationers, Manufacturers and Office Outfitters. 2/1/2028.
      - Item 3: How A Northern Democrat Feels About The Future, 1929; Speech (Box 1, Folder 15)
        3/5/29.
      - Item 4: What Employers Can Do To Prevent Unemployment, 1931; Speech (Box 1, Folder 15)
        1/15/31.
      - Item 5: Untitled Address (before the Women's Educational and Industrial Union), 1903; Speech (Box 1, Folder 15)
        4/17/03.
      - Item 6: The Problem of Stabilized Employment, 1931; Speech (Box 1, Folder 15)
        Given at the annual convention of the Association of Government Officials in Industry of the United States and Canada. 5/20/1931.
      - Item 7: State Leadership Toward The Prevention of Unemployment, Massachusetts Commission on the Stabilization of Employment, 1931; Speech (Box 1, Folder 15)
        Before the Massachusetts Conference of Social Work. 9/25/31.
      - Item 8: Untitled Address, 1932; Speech (Box 1, Folder 15)
        At the annual state conference of the Massachusetts Safety Council. 4/20/32.
      - Item 9: Radio Address, 1932; Speech (Box 1, Folder 15)
        Boston American. 5/37/32.
      - Item 10: Extract of Address, 1932; Speech (Box 1, Folder 15)
        Before the annual convention of state branch [Massachusetts], American Federation of Labor. 8/1/1932.
      - Item 11: Inspectors' Function in Promoting Employees Training and Education in Reducing Work Injuries, 1905; Speech (Box 1, Folder 15)
        4/15/1905.
      - Item 12: The Relationship of the Massachusetts Courts to the Forty-Four Hour Law, Speech (Box 1, Folder 15)
        (n.d.).
    - Speeches, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Item 1: Opening Address, 1933; Speech (Box 1, Folder 16)
        Before the Second Interstate Conference on Labor Laws. 1/27/1933.
      - Item 2: Radio Talk, 1933; Speech (Box 1, Folder 16)
        New England Council. 2/7/1933.
      - Item 3: The Labor Department Inspector's Part in Promoting Employee Education for Prevention of Work Injuries, 1933; Speech (Box 1, Folder 16)
        Before the Fourth Annual Greater New York Safety Conference. 3/1/33.
      - Item 4: A Defense of the Thirty-Hour Bill, 1933; Speech (Box 1, Folder 16)
        4/21/1933.
      - Item 5: Untitled Address, 1933; Speech (Box 1, Folder 16)
        Before the American Federation of Labor Convention at Springfield. 8/7/1933.
      - Item 6: Meeting at Taunton, 1933; Speech (Box 1, Folder 16)
        Discharged Moulders. 8/30/1933.
    - Speeches, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Item 1: Section 7 (A), 1934; Speech (Box 1, Folder 17)
        Before the New England Conference. 11/23/34.
    - Speeches, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Item 1: Radio Address, 1935; Speech (Box 1, Folder 18)
        Ft. Worth, Texas. 2/7/1935.
      - Item 2: Press Release of Speech, 1935; Speech (Box 1, Folder 18)
        Before the Regional Labor Board, 7th District, New Orleans, Louisiana. 2/7/1935.
      - Item 3: Press Release of Speech, 1935; Speech (Box 1, Folder 18)
        Before the Regional Labor Board, 13th District, Ft. Worth, Texas. 2/8/1935.
      - Item 4: Untitled Address, 1935; Speech (Box 1, Folder 18)
        Before the Consumers League of Massachusetts. 3/8/1935.
      - Item 5: Notes on Company Unions, 1935; Speech (Box 1, Folder 18)
        Testimony on the Wagner Bill. 3/18/35.
      - Item 6: Should Government Foster Organization of Labor?, 1935; Speech (Box 1, Folder 18)
        Before the Commonwealth Club of California, San Francisco. 5/10/1935.
    - Speeches, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Item 1: Statement, 1936; Speech (Box 1, Folder 19)
        Before Hearings of Subcommittee, on Senate Resolution 266. 4/23/1936.
      - Item 2: Statement for release in next issue of Labor, 1936; Speech (Box 1, Folder 19)
        5/23/36.
      - Item 3: Portland Radio Talk, 1936; Speech (Box 1, Folder 19)
        5/36.
      - Item 4: Untitled Speech, 1936; Speech (Box 1, Folder 19)
        Before the Massachusetts State Federation of Labor, New Bedford. 8/4/1936.
    - Speeches, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Item 1: Untitled Address, 1937; Speech (Box 1, Folder 20)
        Before the American Federation of Hosiery Workers Convention. 1/28/1937.
      - Item 2: Untitled Address, 1937; Speech (Box 1, Folder 20)
        Before the National Conference of Social Work, Indianapolis, Indiana. 5/28/1937.
      - Item 3: Adjustment of Industrial Disputes, 1937; Speech (Box 1, Folder 20)
        Before the International Association of Governmental Labor Officials, Toronto. 9/1/1937.
      - Item 4: How the National Labor Relations Board Administers the Wagner Act, 1937; Speech (Box 1, Folder 20)
        24th Annual National Business Conference, Babson's Institute, Wellesley Hills, Massachusetts 10/6/37.
      - Item 5: Excerpt from Address, 1937; Speech (Box 1, Folder 20)
        Before the Associated Industries of New York State, Inc. 11/11/1937.
    - Speeches, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Item 1: Civil Rights for Labor, 1938; Speech (Box 1, Folder 21)
        Before the American Civil Liberties Union. 1/4/1938.
      - Item 2: The Demand for Regulation of Labor Unions, 1938; Speech (Box 1, Folder 21)
        Before the International Juridical Association. 1/15/1938.
      - Item 3: The National Labor Relations Act - Guardian of Democracy, 1938; Speech (Box 1, Folder 21)
        Before the Carolina Political Union, Durham, North Carolina. 3/30/1938.
      - Item 4: The Drive Against the National Labor Relations Board, 1938; Speech (Box 1, Folder 21)
        Before the 2nd Convention of the United Office and Professional Workers of America. 5/21/1938.
      - Item 5: Extracts from Speech, 1938; Speech (Box 1, Folder 21)
        Before the convention of Oil Workers International Union, Houston, Texas. 6/7/38.
      - Item 6: Excerpts from Talk, 1938; Speech (Box 1, Folder 21)
        Before the San Antonio Manufacturers Association. 6/8/38.
      - Item 7: The National Labor Relations Board and Business, 1938; Speech (Box 1, Folder 21)
        Before the Harvard Business School Alumni Association. 6/18/1938.
      - Item 8: Untitled Speech, 1938; Speech (Box 1, Folder 21)
        Before the American Communications Association Convention. 7/22/38.
      - Item 9: Statement of Board Member Edwin S. Smith, 1938; Speech (Box 1, Folder 21)
        re William Green's attack. 8/6/1938.
      - Item 10: Government and the Trade Unions - An Analysis of Experience in Administering the National Labor Relations Act, 1938; Speech (Box 1, Folder 21)
        Before the International Industrial Relations Institute Regional Study Conference, Mexico City. 9/3/38.
      - Item 11: Excerpts from Speeches regarding the courts, 1938; Speech (Box 1, Folder 21)
        Before the Massachusetts Conference of Social Work. 11/30/1938.
    - Speeches, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Item 1: The National Labor Relations Act in the Democratic Crisis, 1939; Speech (Box 1, Folder 22)
        Before the Church League for Industrial Democracy, Boston, Massachusetts. 2/13/1939.
      - Item 2: Excerpts from Speech, 1939; Speech (Box 1, Folder 22)
        Presented at a town meeting on the National Labor Relations Act, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. 3/30/1939.
      - Item 3: What Sort of Liberalism Do We Want?, 1939; Speech (Box 1, Folder 22)
        Before the Liberal Club Conference, Williams College, Williamstown, Massachusetts. 5/5/1939.
      - Item 4: Statement, 1939; Speech (Box 1, Folder 22)
        Before the Senate Committee on Education and Labor in connection with proposed amendments to the National Labor Relations Act. 6/5/1939.
      - Item 5: Untitled Address, 1939; Speech (Box 1, Folder 22)
        At the 5th Convention of United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America. 9/5/1939.
      - Item 6: Untitled Address, 1939; Speech (Box 1, Folder 22)
        Before the Second Annual Biennial Convention of Transport Workers Union. 9/20/1939.
    - Speeches, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Item 1: Civil Liberties in the Present Crisis, 1940; Speech (Box 1, Folder 23)
        Before the Civil Liberties Committee of Massachusetts. 1/27/1940.
      - Item 2: The National Labor Relations Board, 1940; Speech (Box 1, Folder 23)
        Before the Harvard Law School Students. 3/8/1940.
      - Item 3: Civil Liberties and National Defense, 1940; Speech (Box 1, Folder 23)
        Before the National Conference on Constitutional Liberties in America. 6/9/1940.
      - Item 4: Statement, 1940; Speech (Box 1, Folder 23)
        Before the House Committee on Labor in connection with proposed amendments to the National Labor Relations Act. 7/40.
      - Item 5: Untitled Address, 1940; Speech (Box 1, Folder 23)
        Before the convention of the International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers, Denver, Colorado. 8/5/40.
      - Item 6: Untitled Address, 1940; Speech (Box 1, Folder 23)
        Before the Committee for People's Rights, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. 10/15/1940.
      - Item 7: The National Labor Relations Act and Its Administration, 1940; Speech (Box 1, Folder 23)
        Before the Indianapolis Chamber of Commerce. 10/31/1940.
      - Item 8: Untitled Address, 1940; Speech (Box 1, Folder 23)
        Before the State Convention of Maryland and District of Columbia Industrial Union Council, Hagerstown, Maryland. 12/14/1940.
    - Speeches, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Item 1: The National Labor Relations Act and Its Administration, 1941; Speech (Box 1, Folder 24)
        Before the Harvard, Yale and Princeton Engineering Associations, La Guardia Airport. 1/17/1941.
      - Item 2: Democracy in Crisis, 1941; Speech (Box 1, Folder 24)
        Before the New York Conference for Inalienable Rights, New York City. 2/14/1941.
      - Item 3: Address at the Lawyers Guild Dinner in Honor of Judge J. Warren Madden, 1941; Speech (Box 1, Folder 24)
        2/22/1941.
      - Item 4: Democracy and Academic Freedom, 1941; Speech (Box 1, Folder 24)
        Testimonial Dinner to Dr. Franz Boas. 3/12/1941.
      - Item 5: Untitled Address, 1941; Speech (Box 1, Folder 24)
        Before the annual luncheon meeting of the New York College Teachers Union. 5/3/41.
      - Item 6: The Current Attack on Our Civil Liberties, 1941; Speech (Box 1, Folder 24)
        Before the 5th annual convention of the National Lawyers Guild, Detroit, Michigan. 5/31/1941.
      - Item 7: The Newspaper Guild and the Wagner Act, 1941; Speech (Box 1, Folder 24)
        Before the 8th annual convention of the American Newspaper Guild, Detroit, Michigan. 6/25/1941.
      - Item 8: The Significance of Labor Day 1941, Speech (Box 1, Folder 24)
        Before the Western Maryland Labor Day Celebration, Cumberland, Maryland. 9/1/1941.
      - Item 9: Labor in the Present Crisis, 1941; Speech (Box 1, Folder 24)
        Before the annual convention of the Transport Workers Union of America, New York City. 9/24/1941.
      - Item 10: The War and Labor's Civil Rights, 1941; Speech (Box 1, Folder 24)
        Before the Education Conference of the Indiana State Industrial Union Council. 12/14/1941.
      - Item 11: Statement in Reply to Final Report of the Special Committee to Investigate the National Labor Relations Board, 1905; Speech (Box 1, Folder 24)
        4/24/1905.
      - Item 12: Labor and the War, 1942; Speech (Box 1, Folder 24)
        Delivered at the Anniversary Dinner of the International Juridical Association. 3/2/1942.
      - Item 13: Labor, the War and the Poll Tax, 1942; Speech (Box 1, Folder 24)
        Before Jefferson's Birthday Meeting of the National Committee to Abolish the Poll Tax. 4/13/1942.
    - Speeches, 1950-1953 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Item 1: Untitled Address, 1950; Speech (Box 1, Folder 25)
        Delivered at the New York University Symposium, sponsored by the Young Progressives of America. 5/17/1950.
      - Item 2: Testimony of Smith before Subcommittee to Investigate the Administration of the Internal Security Act And Other Internal Security Laws., 1953; Speech (Box 1, Folder 25)
        5/21/1953.
      - Item 3: Civil Liberties in the Present Crisis, Speech (Box 1, Folder 25)
        Before a Mass Meeting of the National Action Conference for Civil Rights held under the auspices of the National Federation for Constitutional Liberties and the Washington Committee for Democratic Action) Untitled Speech (audience unknown and date incomplete.
    - Articles and Speeches Indexes:, 1928-1941 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Smith's chronological listing of "Groups Before Which Edwin S. Smith Has Spoken." Also handwritten list of speeches and articles. Typed list of speeches.
      - Item 1: Articles and Speeches Indexes:, 1928-1941; Speech (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Sub-Series C. Writings
    - Burdenz, Louis. (Box 1, Folder 26a)
      Series of 10 articles written by Smith on Burdenz and the Communist Party.
    - Civil Liberties of Teachers., 1949-1951 (Box 1, Folder 27-29)
      Drafts of eight articles relating to violations of academic freedom. Includes discussion of the Feinberg Acts and loyalty oaths; letters to the New York Times Editor; testimony at the hearings on the Master Plan of the Board of Trustees, State University of New York, Albany; statement on the Interrogation of Teachers Union Officials by Superintendent of Schools William Jansen; statement entitled Support of Foreign Teachers for New York Teachers Union in Its Struggle Against Timone Resolution and Suspension of 8 Teachers; "What's Happening to Your Children, Your School and Your Teachers" March of Labor.
    - Coal Industry., 1949 (Box 1, Folder 30-35)
      Drafts and final copies of ten articles written for The Daily Compass, examining the conditions under which miners live and work.
    - CIO., 1949 (Box 1, Folder 36-42)
      Drafts and final versions of four articles written for The Daily Compass, the series entitled "The CIO in Crisis". Includes discussion of the CIO and the World Federation of Trade Unions (WFTU). Paper entitled "Labor Gains Recognition" concerns CIO strikes in 1935.
    - History of Labor., 1962 (Box 1, Folder 43-44)
      Early format of manuscript includes annotated, edited drafts of forward; some of the text (annotated) which is divided into Books I, II, and III, containing chapters I and II, IV, VI respectively.
    - History of Labor., 1962 (Box 1, Folder 45-46)
      Includes revised draft of forward; early list of chapter headings and revised list of chapter headings.
    - History of Labor., 1962 (Box 1, Folder 47-63)
      Chapters I-XXX; Over 800 pages of typewritten text, surveying American labor history from Colonial times up to the Cold War era. Very little editing, possibly a near final version of the manuscript.
    - History of Labor., 1962 (Box 2, Folder 1-8)